[Music]
do
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the
final double digit episode of ask
abhijit
great to have you all with me and
as always lots of lots and lots of
questions
i have selected a bunch of these and
let's get right into the questions that
you have asked
so what's question number one
question number one is by kevin chenoy
in the future when india's gdp grows
phenomenally well our hard power will
become massively visible to the world
so will then
india be able to take russia out of the
chinese orbit the current dragon bear
alliance
will it also result in a more profound
relationship between india and russia
the tiger bear alliance
leading to a world free of american and
chinese influence in each nation's
internal
matters
in the future when india becomes more
powerful when india's gdp grows
phenomenally well in the next 10 20
years
things will be different india will be
able to do whatever it wants it's like
when a poor person becomes rich
they can uplift whoever they want they
can take along whoever they want whoever
their friends are whoever their allies
are they can do good things for them
similarly when india is in that position
of being a prosperous nation rich nation
powerful nation it will be able
to bring other uh but other countries
along with it
and uh in case india russia relations
are still good at the time and we still
have
uh
mutual interests and mutual benefits
then certainly india would be able to
take russia along
with itself
and i don't see any reason why india and
russia would not have
good relations let's say 20 years in the
future because india and russia are
actually natural allies
unlike certain other countries that we
term as natural allies these days india
and russia are actually natural allies
we have
a common adversary which is china which
is the common neighbor to both countries
india and russia and we have lots of
other interests there are lots of
resources that russia has that india
could
obtain from russia and there's lots of
benefits that india can offer to russia
as well so in the future maybe 10 or 20
years down the line we could very much
see the emergence of a tiger bear
alliance that's a very interesting name
that you have
put out kevin
so yes there could be a world see
currently if you look at the us
the u.s whether people like it or not
the us is a nation it's an empire that's
in decline the us of the 2020s is like
the uk of the 20 of the 1930s and 1940s
a nation in slow gradual decline a
nation that was once all powerful
but which is now showing signs of
decline there was the uk in the 1930s
and later in the 1940s and that seems to
be the situation of the us right now
so in the future you may have
a
tiger bear alliance
and a russia in a world that is maybe
less dependent on the us and in china it
all depends on a variety of factors on
what sort of in leadership india has
what sort of leadership russia has what
sort of leadership china and the u.s has
what moves they make
what pieces fall into which place on the
global geopolitical chess board and all
that but yes it is certainly possible so
that's a very interesting
question that you have asked and then
interesting
term that you have coined kevin the
tiger bear alliance
okay rama lakshmi says recently russia
tested its sarmat satan 2 icbm
intercontinental ballistic missile
if such ballistic missiles with nuclear
warheads are fired hypothetically at
russia
can the defense system such as the s 400
or the patriot insert intercept them and
if they did such high yield massage what
could would be the impact in air as the
warhead would explode and do you think
radiation would spread
okay let's first take the second part of
the question let's say you have
a nuclear missile that's incoming
and you take it out with an anti-missile
missile
let's say with the s-400 system or some
other missile defense system india has
its own indigenous anti-missile systems
like the prithvi air defense system and
so on so it's like shooting a bullet
with a bullet that's what it's like
so let's say you have an inter incoming
intercontinental ballistic missile
what what an icbm does or any ballistic
missile does is that it first goes out
of the earth's atmosphere goes on a
ballistic trajectory which is
essentially a projectile motion a
parabolic path and then it re-enters the
atmosphere and then it
comes towards the destination whatever
the target is
so that's what a ballistic missile is
like so when it re-enters the atmosphere
that's when you can intercept it
when you know where it's uh heading
towards it depends on what sort of range
your missiles your missile defense
system has what is the readiness and so
on so forth but let's say you
take one of these incoming missiles out
you destroy it
this incoming missile is a nuclear
missile let's say it has a nuclear
warhead so when you destroy the incoming
nuclear missile
will there be a nuclear explosion
no
most likely it won't there won't be a
nuclear explosion there is something
called a fuse on a nuclear warhead and
it typically detonates
and the nuclear warhead on a missile
incoming ballistic missile typically
detonates at a certain altitude or on
impact
and there are certain characteristics of
the impact that would trigger a
detonation
most probably it would be something that
is a proximity kind of thing maybe 100
meters above when the altitude is is 100
meters or maybe half a kilometer or
whatever whatever you programmed into it
so that's what it takes for a nuclear
explosion to happen and for the warheads
nuclear device to be triggered most
likely when you take out a nuclear
missile which is incoming in mid-air we
would typically do it at an altitude of
50 kilometers or 20 kilometers if you're
or something like that something like
that so in that case most likely there
will not be a nuclear explosion it will
just be destroyed and the warhead will
fall somewhere or maybe it will break
open and then and the materials inside
may
may spill out into the atmosphere so
that is the most likely scenario maybe
maybe there even may be a nuclear blast
in case it is programmed that way in
which case the nuclear explosion will
take several kilometers up in the air
and it will not have a significant
impact on the target site let's say you
have a nuclear blast 10 kilometers in
the air or 20 kilometers high up in
there there'll be almost no fallout on
the ground there will be a cloud of
radioactive debris and all that it will
dissipate across the atmosphere and it
will
lead to well the kind of situation you
had when the
tsar bomba was detonated so the russians
they detonated this enormous nuclear
bomb the tsar bomba
i think it was in the 50s or 60s most
likely somewhere around that time and
this
50 megaton nuclear warhead was detonated
maybe a few kilometers in the air i'm
not sure what height it was at
but maybe let's say let's say
hypothetically 10 kilometers or 5
kilometers whatever it was so it
exploded in mid air
and then it
created a massive mushroom cloud but the
fallout the radioactive fallout was very
less on the ground it was negligible
of course there was a radioactive
fallout in the atmosphere but that's a
different story so it
if a nuclear warhead explodes in mid-air
a few kilometers above the ground it
will not have much of an effect
on the target site
that's what happens so uh now
about the sarmat icbm that's a
super heavy icbm it's a double it's it
has at least two stages the first stage
i believe is a solid draw solid fueled
stage
and the the second stage or whatever it
is or third stage whatever it is is a
liquid fueled stage
and it has a very very long range it can
essentially hit any target in the world
so that's what it is
now can a defense system such as the
s400 or the patriot system intercept it
the thing about the sarmat is is that it
is an enormous missile it's a super
heavy missile it has a very long range
and it is a mirv missile multiple
independent re-entry vehicles which
means that a single missile would carry
maybe 10 or 12
thermonuclear warheads
and each of these warheads would be pro
will be programmed to hit a different
destination a different target
so the missile goes up into the
atmosphere it goes out of the atmosphere
goes into
into
into space outer space then it re-enters
the atmosphere and while re-entering
it it's uh
it releases the 10 12 15 whatever
warheads it is carrying and each of
these warheads goes into a different
goes to a different destination
and sometimes you may even have a
maneuverable maneuvering
uh
gliding warhead
that would go to a destination but it
would go through a zigzag path so it's
very hard to intercept right
so that is the advantage of having mirv
technology multiple independent re-entry
vehicles or
i think that's what the acronym stands
for
so when you have that sort of a thing
it's really hard to intercept that
you will essentially have to either
destroy the incoming missile very high
in the atmosphere before it releases
its warheads
or you would have to
go after each forehead independently
let's say it releases 15 warheads or 12
warheads each of which is a
thermonuclear weapon
and each of these guys goes in different
directions it may be each of these guys
may be maneuvering in a certain way it
makes it really really hard to intercept
really hard
now the s 400 system
may possibly able be able to
take out
these mirv warheads possibly i think
it's able to target multiple
incoming
bogies at the same time
so it is certainly possible that the
s400 may be able to take it out there's
a newer more advanced version of the
of the system called the s500 this even
talk about s550
so
these are
progressively better iterations of the
system the previous one was called the
s300
so uh
there's always a likelihood that even
the best system may miss some of the
incoming
missiles of warheads
because none of these systems is
guaranteed to be 100 accurate it has
a small error margin
and the s400 is
as of today most likely the best
available system the patriot system is
not quite as good neither is the israeli
iron dome system
so i think if you want to if you are a
betting person if you would like to bet
then your bets should be on the s400
system because i think the s400 system
has the best possible
chance of stopping an incoming nuclear
attack even if it is an mirv system i
believe it's able to take out it's able
to deal with
mirved warheads as well so
if you want to bet you should bet on the
s400
this is by vishal what do you think
about dictators like mao citung joseph
stalin king il-sung
were the good leaders for their
countries
interesting question so
these are dictators like you say
autocrats dictators iron men etc that's
what you would call them
i would not categorize kim il-sung
in the same category or the same bracket
as mao tong and joseph stalin kim
il-sung is a different kind of dictator
so joseph stalin was the strong men of
the ussr the
most powerful dictator they had
and the one who had the most massive
impact impact on the country on the
geopolitics of europe and of eurasia
yeah
mao zedong was the guy who
essentially brought the chinese
communist party to power and he's the
guy he can be considered to be the
founding father of the modern nation of
communist china right so these guys
one could put them in the same bracket
or same category kim il-sung
was certainly
the dictator of north korea the for the
founding member of founding father of
the of the kim dynasty
his son his son's name was kim jong-il
and his grandson's name is kim jong-un
who is the current dictator of north
korea well kim il-sung
derived his power from outside forces he
was essentially a puppet
of
of china and the ussr indirectly ussr
indirectly china
so that's what he was without the
support the external support of a
massive player like china
kim il-sung had no legitimacy and no
power his entire power was derived from
outside support so he was essentially a
puppet that's what he was of course he
was all-powerful within his country
but if he did not
obey the orders of his overlord then he
was going to be gone in a minute that's
how it was
so kim il-sung
derived his power from outside support
mao zedong had his own power base in
china
and joseph stalin also had his own power
base in the ussr so these two guys were
different now all three were dictators
all three were desperate
right
as we know joseph stalin did all kinds
of terrible terrible atrocities
in
his country
outside his country as well
i mean if you think of if you
if you talk about the
the cutting massacre of the second world
war which was blamed on the nazis but it
was then revealed that the ussr did that
it was done on the orders of joseph
stalin
i think it was vasily blokhin the
world's most infamous executioner who
carried it out
and we know about the terrible famine in
the ukraine the holodomor
and all kinds of terrible purges that he
carried out and i don't know how many
millions of people either directly or
indirectly died at the
on the orders or at the hands of
joseph stalin
there's also his commissars like yejov
and
what was the guy's name
there was this guy called
yejov who was his head of the nkvd i
think or the head of the secret secret
police
and before yejof there was another guy
they were all eliminated
so it was a tyrannical rule right that's
that's the kind of rule that joseph
stalin had in the ussr very very brutal
rule but of course he industrialized the
ussr and he transformed the country
through brute force and through a
variety of methods into a genuine
superpower one of the two superpowers in
the world
so on the one hand his rule was brutal
one could say barbaric inhuman and so on
and so forth he impoverished
tens of millions of people in his
country maybe hundreds of millions of
billions of people in this country
and he
well his rule
he mismanaged a lot of stuff and
it cost a lot of lives too many lives
right and the same thing can be said
about martha tong
he
his rule was also very brutal
i mean
he may have ended up killing
maybe almost 100 million of his own
country people through a variety of
terribly bungled plants and
all kinds of things right the the
famines that he
created the artificial famines it caused
the so-called great leap forward the
so-called cultural revolution it was
these are all enormous massive disasters
for china
tens of millions of people died in these
ridiculous schemes that he
that he created
so
yeah i mean the human cost was terrible
and yet
the policies he followed they were the
platform upon which
then dropping then shopping essentially
took
took the country forward
so what he the the
what he created for thing shopping was
this this
countrywide
one-party rule
which then sharping was able to leverage
in order to take china forward and
that's why china is like
well
the most powerful nation and the most
prosperous nation in eurasia today
so it was all because of things shopping
but then shopping would not have been
able to do do what he did
had it not been for the state machinery
that mao don't been built
so these guys
stalin mouth they left behind mixed
legacies
they
killed way too many people they caused
the deaths of way too many people tens
of millions maybe
over 100 million people they caused
incredible amounts of
misery
right
and suffering
unnecessary suffering but they also
eventually led to the rise of their
countries in in
in an aggregate
fashion
so it's a mixed legacy obviously when
one would not wish
such leaders
on any other country
one certainly would not wish that sort
of a leader in any civilized country
right
so yeah that's what i can say about
these three individuals kim's kim
il-sung was nothing compared to these
two guys
mao zedong and joseph
stalin
ayan says what are the views of science
on yoga in ayurveda
yoga and ayurveda are very very ancient
systems that go back several thousand
years
right indian systems that emerged out of
ancient india
if you if you
you find the earliest evidence of yoga
in statutes from the
saraswati sindhu phase of indian
civilization that goes back five six
thousand years before today so that's
how old yoga is and most likely ayurveda
also would be that old
so these are very ancient systems that
they well predate any other
system of of healthcare
the chinese like to tout their
traditional chinese medicine
well the indian ayurveda and yoga go way
before the chinese medicine they predate
china itself
if you look at china china
if you
look at the history of chinese
civilization the
attested the recorded history of chinese
civilization goes back about three three
and a half thousand years yeah
so yoga and ayurveda predate china
itself as a
civilization uh now what the chinese
have been able to do is that they have
been able to bring traditional chinese
medicine into the modern age
there are all kinds of herbs and
remedies that are available in ancient
chinese medicine and they have been able
to
what they've done is that they have
researched these herbs and remedies
through
the means through the through the
using the methods of modern science 20th
century science to even 21st century
science and one of the most important
anti-malarial drugs
artemisin i think it's called i'm not
sure what the exact name is the
commercial name of that is falci go i
think
that was discovered through research
done on ancient chinese
herbal
remedies for malaria right
so there's a great deal of potential in
ancient chinese medicine well i would
say there's a even more potential
in ayurveda if it is properly researched
and the various hubs
and other
preparations and treatments are
investigated
scientifically i mean what are the
active compounds that are at work in
various substances on various herbs like
brahmi for instance brahmi is well known
to increase your your
mental acuity your alertness maybe even
the level of your intelligence and so on
but nobody has bothered to do any
research on brahmi
right brahmi and there are so many other
horrible remedies from ayurveda and so
on but
in recent times
people have indeed started doing
some
research
into ayurveda and let me show you an
example
of that
so let me share my screen
and here we are this is
once it comes on screen this is a
research paper that has been published
in
nature
as you can see nature scientific reports
this is from 2015.
genome-wide analysis
correlates ayurveda prakriti so let me
just read out the abstract for you the
practice of ayurveda the traditional
medicine of india is based on the
concept of three major constitutional
types vata and kapha defined as prakriti
to the best of our knowledge no study
has convincingly correlated
genomic variations with the
classification of prakriti
in the present study we performed
genome-wide snp single nucleotide
polymorphism analysis
of 262 well-classified male individuals
belonging to three prakritis
and so on and so forth
so we found 52 snps were significantly
different
between prakritis without any
confounding effect of certification
after 10 raise to 6 permutations
principal component analysis of these
snps classified 260 262 individuals into
their respective groups vata
irrespective of their ancestry which
represent its power in categorization we
further validated our finding with 297
indian population samples with known
ancestry
subsequently we found that pgm1
correlates with the phenotype of pitta
as described in the ancient text of
character suggesting that the phenotypic
classification of india's class
traditional medicine has a genetic basis
and it's prakriti based practice in
vogue for many centuries especially
actually millennia
resonates with personalized medicine so
this is where you find the genetic
genome analysis correlates ayurveda
prakriti there's a more recent article
from springer
uh from 2018 which also talks about this
translational potential of ayurveda
prakriti concepts in the area of
personalized medicine
so this concludes by saying that the
east welcomes the west to personalized
medicine and it also kind of co
corroborates
uh the ayurvedic classification of
individuals into various prakritis
but
so as you can see there is
indeed a genuine scientific basis to
ayurveda you would also find the same
thing in yoga i mean there have been
some studies done on about on the
beneficial effects of yoga on on the
human body the human mind meditation and
so on so forth and they have they have
certainly found i have don't have the
result here because i've not looked it
up right now but
check it out google it search for it and
you will find studies that are done and
that do demonstrate that yoga yoga too
has beneficial effects on
on human well-being
so there are indeed in recent times
scientific studies that are now being
carried out slowly
on
ayurveda and yoga and
these studies do
confirm that
both of these systems yoga and ayurveda
have beneficial effects on human
well-being
so that's what i can say about this in
brief
okay
shiva says namaste my question to you is
about hindu kush mountain
was it known by another name before it
was known as hindukush
i read that it is named after lord
rama's son kosh but afghans mainly refer
to it as killer of hindus as per the
language why would a mountain river or
anything which was part of our territory
be named like that it's a disgrace
my partner who is in afghan whenever i
told him that afghans especially except
for hazaras and uzbeks have indian
ancestry he got severely offended and
denied it
they live here i mean in india but their
hatred towards india is unbelievable
and behave as if india owes them some
favor
instead of being grateful why do we the
government even allow these people to
live here
okay
okay there's a whole lot to unpack here
the hindu kush mountain
the name hindu kush means the killer of
hindus
in persian i believe that is undeniable
the hindu kush mountain means the killer
of hindus it's not a single mountain
it's a mountain range
and it's known as the killer of hindus i
think the first person to call it
hindu kush or the killer of hindus
in writing in the in the
written record was the
north african traveler ibn batuta he was
an islamic traveler who traveled who
traveled to india and various other
places and he is the guy
who called this mountain this mountain
range the hindu kush mountain range
and why was it called the hindu kush
mountain range because when the turks
invaded and occupied india they carried
back
tens of thousands maybe hundreds of
thousands maybe millions of indians
indian slaves mainly
women and children
as slaves out of india into turkistan
central asia to se into into the into
arabia also possibly to sell them as
slaves for various purposes
and indians were accustomed to the warm
climate of india and these mountains
were frightfully cold and
incredible numbers of indians died
while being forcibly made to cross these
mountains and go into central asia
so so many indians died in these in this
mountain range that it came to be known
as the hindu kush the killer of hindus
when you say indians you mean hindus
only hindus were carried out of india as
slaves women and children mostly also
some men
which was a well that's how it goes
and i'm sure that if today historians
and archaeologists especially
archaeologists were to go to the
mountain range
maybe do some digging or something they
would find frozen preserved bodies of
ancient indians there
women and children mostly so that is why
it is called hindu kush what is the
original name of this mountain range it
was known
in civilized days
when afghanistan was gandhar it was part
of the indian subcontinent and part of
indian civilization in those days this
mountain rage was known as the upari
shayna mountain range upari
the place where eagles also cannot fly
it is beyond the reach of eagles
sheen in sanskrit means eagle
it was also known as opericien
in the old persian language
because persian the old persian language
was more or less the same as sanskrit it
was a descendant a slightly corrupted
version of sanskrit
and the mountain range name was the same
in the old persian
uparishina
where
the place that is beyond the reach of
eagles
and it's interesting that the word shane
of sanskrit the sanskrit word shein
got corrupted into the persian word
shaheen
so shaheen is a persian word
it it today denotes various kinds of
raptors i think hawks
but it originally meant
eagles
sheena so this mountain range was called
the upari sheena mountain range
that was the true name the original name
now it's known as the hindu kush because
of
the events of the past 1000 years
now the afghans well the afghans will
never accept that their ancestors were
indians or hindus
uh
the majority population in in
afghanistan in gandhar is the pashtun
people are the pashtun people
you also have uzbeks and and turkmens
and hazaras and
tajiks in afghanistan because of the
event of the past 1000 years lots of
turks came into afghanistan into gandhar
and settled down there so you have a
multi multitude of ethnic groups there
the
major ethnic group is the pashtuns they
are the descendants of ancient indians
genetic analysis shows that of course
there will be intermingling of some kind
with various other ethnic groups that
have
introgressed into gandhar over time
but if you tell afghans especially
pashtuns that your ancestors were
indians they were hindus or buddhists
they will deny it and they will get
offended that's the
that's the overall
uh
attitude they have they they they like
to claim that they are the descendants
of of of ancient jews apparently
well uh not a single genetic analysis
has been able to dredge out even in
an iota of
of jewish ancestry among the pashtuns
the pashtuns are essentially an
outgrowth of the overall northern and
western indian indian population
genetically they are more or less the
same
and
so that's what the history is now they
get off they get offended and
you're saying that your partner is an
afghan he lives in india but hates india
well
why is it like this it's because of what
has been what they've been taught over
the past 1000 years they've been taught
to
hate their ancestry their culture their
original culture and
to see themselves as
something else
so that's just how it is
right
so why does the government even allow
these people to live here well
i do not speak on behalf of the
government so i don't know
one should not allow people to live in
india
especially
the kind of people who hate india i mean
that's that's i think that's just
plain logic
but well that's just how it is that's
where we are today
things will change slowly
all right
okay next question christoph
frischkorn says what impact would the
election of marine le pen have on the eu
nato and the war in ukraine
so let's understand who madame marine le
pen is she is a far right
political leader in france
i don't remember the name of her
political party it was her the political
party that she heads
was founded her by her papa
monsieur marie lupin so when i was a
little kid miss you joe marie le pen was
the head of the
uh that political party he was a extreme
right-winger far-right
nationalist
and i believe that in the early 2000s he
uh
he he i think he stood for uh for the
post of president of france on a number
of occasions four or five times in the
early 2000s he made a very serious bid
and
and he came quite close apparently right
so that is uh
her daddy
miss you jean-marie le pen
and eventually her father was expelled
from the party by his daughter nareen le
pen for whatever reason so it was like a
internal coup in the
dynastic coup within the party and now
she is the
head of the party the president of the
party i think or whatever the position
is so that in short is who
marine le pen is now she is a
hard
right-winger
in the context of european politics
french politics she's a hard nationalist
uh she is not a frontrunner for for
winning the election most likely mr
mcconnell will win but in case madam
marine le pen wins this election
then politics will change uh
she has expressed
uh
her intention
of taking france out of nato i mean i'm
not sure if she even if she gets elected
she'll succeed in doing that but that's
what she wants
she wants to bring france out of nato
because she sees with i think with good
reason
the position of france within nato as
being that of a u.s vasal state which
actually it is right
any country that is part of nato is
subsidiary to the us and under the
direct military orders
of the united states
so france is the one of the members of
nato i believe
that france is maybe the only member of
nato
it is not maybe it is definitely the
only member of nato that has an
independent foreign policy and there is
a cause of severe friction between
france and the uk in the united states
the u.s uh americans love to
denigrate france as a nation of what
what do they call them uh this is not my
words they call them surrender monkeys
like you guys surrendered to the nazis
and we had to bail you out in the second
world war that's the kind of
uh
that's that's what the french are told
and
so on so forth so the americans kind of
enjoy taunting the french about this
and uh
so so the french feel disrespected the
french don't like to speak english even
if
they even if they know english they will
not want to speak english you go to
paris people will refuse many people
will refuse to speak in english to you
and so on
so
marine le pen wants to bring france out
of nato if she wins the election
she may try to do that i'm not sure how
successful she would be
the us would certainly not not like that
u.s and france have had lots of
frictions in in the past
decades
uh the most recent example is the
is the aborted
france australia nuclear submarine deal
not nuclear india but submarine deal the
french had this contract with the
australians the french would sell the
australian the number of scorpene
submarines
it was a signed deal a done deal and
suddenly the australians bailed out of
it and they chose to
acquire nuclear even more expensive
nuclear submarines from the us which
they will get in the 2030s or 2040s i
think
so they ditched a deal they had signed
the americans forced them to do that and
the french were left holding nothing so
the french were really upset about this
they still are
and they don't like being under the
overlord ship of the us
so
marine le pen
if she gets elected the first thing she
would do or one of the major goals she
would have as president of france would
be to bring france out of nato uh maybe
not out of the eu
the so the nato is a bunch of u.s fossil
states
so is the eu so is the european union
the european union is also
a softer version of nato it's also a
bunch of
american
vasal states
so i would say that her first objective
would be to
to bring france out of nato i don't see
any major effect on the war on ukraine
but nato would be shaken up if she comes
to power
so
that's
the major impact her
hypothetical election to the presidency
would have on
the geopolitics in western europe
okay why does the polaris star not move
that's a good question so
we have to understand that our planet
okay i don't have a sphere but let's
consider this to be a sphere
so our planet it moves around a certain
axis it it rotates around its axis of
rotation
and the axis is like this and the planet
rotates like that around that axis right
so
if you have a star in any direction it's
going to go around you at night it will
start in the east or west or wherever
and it will end up in the opposite
direction over the course of a few hours
because of the rotation of the planet
and we know that the planet rotates once
in roughly 24 hours which is why we have
a 24 hour day night cycle
now
if you have a star which is aligned with
the axis of rotation of the planet
then no matter how much the planet
rotates the star will appear to be in
the same position
so that's the position of polaris it is
the one star that is almost
almost completely aligned
in line with the axis of rotation of our
planet and that's why it does not appear
to move even though the other stars they
move around now the thing is this
uh there is
a phenomenon called the precession of
the equinoxes which means that the
axis of rotation of the planet itself
moves it processes
and i think the cycle
is how many years does it take 23 000 23
000 years
uh it's a certain i think it's 23 000
years i'll look it up i may be wrong i
don't remember exactly what it is but
once in that cycle i mean so
the
axis of rotation of the planet also
changes
very slowly which is why every few
thousand years you have a new pole star
so polaris in a few thousand years will
no longer be the pollster there will be
some other star
for instance the star vega
known as abhijit in sanskrit was the
pole star about 10 or 11 000 years ago
and polaris was not the pole star at the
time and somehow
we seem to have recorded the fact that
this star
vega
was the pole star a whole lot of time
ago
so that's how old ancient i mean indian
indian recorded history is so so
to come back to your question that is
why polaris does not move it does not
appear to move if you measure it very
accurately there will be a slight very
slight wobble because it's not
completely and perfectly aligned with
the axis of rotation of our planet
ashok says why what is the reason for a
planet's orbital tilt so i said that our
planet
its axis of rotation processes once in
23 000 or so years
so it means that
our planet goes around the sun let's say
this is the sun our planet and all of
the planets go
around the sun in
imperfect orbits not circles but squash
circles ellipses right
and if you look at the axis of rotation
of the planet it will not be at 90
degrees it will be slightly tilted most
planets have a slight tilt
compared to the uh
plane of the solar system so why is it
so
when the planets formed their axis of
rotation would have been 90 degrees
at a 90 degree angle with the plane of
of the solar system so why is there a
tilt in most planets now there are
certain planets that have a major tilt
and the reason for that is
impacts
ancient impacts
so what most likely happened is that in
the very distant past maybe two three
almost maybe three and a half or so
billion years before today
our planet was hit by
an ancient proto planet in a massive
collision
and that's how it is believed that the
moon was formed by this ejected material
that went into orbit around the earth
and eventually coalesced into a
satellite which we now know as the moon
so when you have a
collision between two planets the axis
of rotation gets wobbly it gets wobbled
up and that's why it your left behind
you're left with a certain tilt
so if it's a major collision your axis
of rotation may get turned around
completely upside down like i think
uranus is it or neptune one of these two
guys
has a very strange
inclined axis of rotation in the case of
the earth it is slightly inclined
so it's because of ancient collisions
that this incline happened
this tilt
happened asmitha says the epic of
ramayana is found across southeast asia
and the local variations are very
popular
however compared to this the mahabharat
and the bhagavad-gita are not as popular
what could be the reasons
this is a very interesting question
so uh yes like asmr says
there are a variety of versions of the
ramayana are found all across southeast
asia
in burma
in thailand in cambodia in laos in
vietnam in indonesia malaysia and so on
and so forth everywhere there is there
are in bali so there are various local
variations
of the ramayana of the raman story of
the ancient history
of that time right
and it's very popular all across
southeast asia
but the mahabharata does not seem to be
that popular
and neither does the bhagavad-gita seem
to be that popular
but lord rama is very popular and his
story is very popular
so why is so right
so uh
indian culture
first spread to southeast asia
three maybe three and a half thousand
years before today
it spread via the ancient merchants of
kalinga present-day odisha
the people of kalinga
merchants who traded with these far away
places
that spread indian culture
to these places
so
i have a whole different
video about that episode of indian
history
the spread of culture to southeast asia
from india via the merchants of ancient
kalinga
and it is still uh
celebrated even today via the
festival of boita bandhana
so these guys used to go in large
ships and even today that is
commemorated in odisha and there is the
bali also and so on right so it is from
ancient kalinga that indian culture
spread throughout southeast asia and
later there was the conquest by the
chula empire which happened about a
thousand years before today so that was
the second wave of enculturation but by
the time the entirety of southeast asia
was very much indianized and hinduised
and later it was it became buddhist and
so on that's all the same thing more or
less
so
so we know that the ramayana is very
popular i would imagine that
the people of kalinga who went to
southeast asia
would have taken the ramayana with them
and maybe at that time in kalinga in
odisha maybe the mahabharata was not
that popular or prevalent that's that is
one possibility that i can think of i
mean i haven't i don't know of any
historian who has answered this question
that's why it's such a good question you
have asked a question that no historian
has bothered to answer
so i would
i would
conjecture
that maybe in ancient kalinga two and a
half three thousand years before today
the ramayana must have been very popular
and maybe not their mahabharat so much
at that time for whatever reason
and maybe that's why their ramayana
became so popular all across southeast
asia which is strange because
if you look at the kalinga of
1 000 years before today
if you look at the history of kalinga
odisha in the past 1000 years
vaishnavism is a very big deal there
right you had the great uh
the great kavi the great poet
jaidev
who
composed the gita govinda which is a
very very
influential uh
devotional
uh text full of poetry some of it even
made it its way into the
guru grand saheb in punjab
and there is this ongoing tussle between
the people of odisha and bengal about
who really is who really owns jaydev
mahakavi right that sort of thing
so in
more recent times orissa
in orisha you i would say the bhagavad
gita was very popular
as well and because of that the
mahabharata as well but it looks like
that
in ancient times the maha the ramayana
was way more popular and that's perhaps
why
that same popularity was transferred
into southeast asia so that's what i can
conjecture it's something that certainly
deserves
proper research
so very good question
okay vishal says why did the romans not
conquer scotland and ireland that's an
interesting question let's take a look
at the map and let's explain where these
places
actually are
so let us go to the maps
let's go to the map
where is the map here is a map
so where is rome where is scotland where
island
so as you can see this here
is rome this is italy the capital city
is rome which was the capital of the
roman empire
and if you look at scotland and ireland
it's way far away to the north in the
west from italy
this is the uk
this island to the west of the uk is
called ireland
it is currently partitioned into two
parts northern ireland and southern
ireland
the british have this policy of
partitioning every country they hate so
that's what they've done
and to the north of the uk you have
scotland
you have edinburgh glasgow
inverness invercargill aberdeen and so
on so forth so this is scotland
so the question is why did the romans
not
conquer scotland and ireland
uh so the roman conquest of
the british isles begins
with julius caesar julius caesar was
looking to expand
his influence and roman influence in
europe
so he crossed the alps and he went into
what is known as goal which is
present-day france and switzerland and
he carried out all sort of all sorts of
conquests massacres atrocities on the
local people there the celtic peoples
and he is considered to be a great
conqueror but he was a brutal barbarian
the kind of things he did but terrible
anyhow he conquered all these places
and then he crossed the english channel
and he
invaded
the british isles
and he was able to conquer some part of
it and after julius caesar the conquests
continued and they went on further north
and then there was
a wall that was built by who was it was
it hadrian was it somebody else i'm not
sure who it was but one of the roman
emperors built a wall between
his dominion
in present-day uk
and scotland
so i believe that it was
a frontier too far
there was nothing to be gained by
conquering that land it was too cold too
far away
not much grew there the romans
essentially wanted nice fertile lands
for their soldiers for their people to
settle in
places lands where you had lots of
resources whether it is gold whether it
is something else whether it's some
metals whether it is good farmland
whatever so that's the kind of territory
they wanted maybe scotland was just too
hilly if you look at the
the topology of scotland it's full of
hills
scotland is very hilly
uh they call it the highlands of
scotland right
so this is uh
the satellite imagery as you can see
it's a very very hilly region it's not
fertile
farmland it's not a great place to to
live in unless you're a scotsman or
scots woman then it's great for you
and if you unless you're a highlander
and that sort of thing and maybe ireland
was just too far away they would have to
cross the
the irish sea and go all the way there
and what would they get there more wild
people more more celtic tribes and so on
so maybe that's why it was just too far
in in too much trouble so most likely
that's why they did not go that far they
had i mean
they had other other fish to fry they
had the whole of europe to conquer they
conquered much of northern africa they
called the conquered hispania iberia
spain
and all the way to present-day turkey
uh the eastern mediterranean parts of
arabia as well and so on so they they
conquered a huge amount of territory
maybe this
this particular part of the world was
just too far and not maybe not worth the
trouble
so most likely
that's why they did not go there because
it was just not worth the trouble
right
okay
chi-ching says
were there any freedom fighters from the
far east region of india good question
so
what she means is what is colloquially
or popularly known as the northeast
region of india so in case
some of you don't know where is
northeast india or the far east of india
it's here
east of the siliguri corridor east of
present-day bangladesh
that is
the far east of india or the northeast
of india you have arunachal pradesh you
have
sikkim is also part of it you have
darjeeling you have meghalaya you have
manipur nagaland mizoram
and tripura
did i leave something out i hope not
assam of course
so this is northeast india or the far
east far east region of india and were
there any freedom fighters from these
places of course there were but
unfortunately our wonderful great
historians have not really bothered to
record the great deeds of the great
people of the far east of india for
instance there were people who fought
against the turks
in assam you have this great warrior
this great commander great general named
lachit borpoken who fought the turkic
arby's of the great tyrant
the barbaric tyrant aurangzeb right and
defeated them
on the on the uh
the battle of the brahmaputra uh i'm so
that is one great freedom fighter lachit
borpoken a great general great warrior
great leader of assam that's one example
i can tell you that is reasonably well
known nowadays
then
then if you go
further east you come to manipur for
instance
so you have the anglo-manipur war in
1891 i think
in which the the british
fought the kingdom of manipur
defeated it and annexed it so you had
great warriors from manipur the
the yuvraj of manipur beer kinderjeet
singh and his great general thangal
general
they fought the british they fought
heroically they were of course defeated
and they were both
hanged by the british
in the middle of the city of imphal
right there's this place
where it happened it is still it is
still there the place where this hanging
happened
so the manipuris fought the british two
of their great warriors the the great
heroes were beer thickened singh and uh
general
and of course from nagaland there was
this lady called
rani guiding you right
she fought against the british
occupation
of india
in the 1920s 30s 40s thereabouts and she
was given the title of rani by the great
shri jawalan
so she was another very famous
freedom fighter from nagaland and there
must have been so many more but
unfortunately i
i don't know of all of them
and
also we know that uh
when the indian national army of the
great
of the great son of india subwashed in
the bose when the ina
invaded
british india in order to liberate india
there were two great battles the battle
of imphal and the battle of kohima
which were part of the second world war
and lots of people from this region from
present-day manipur from from
present-day nagaland they helped the
soldiers of the ina in a variety of ways
whether it's by giving them shelter
whether it's by giving them
food resources whatever they all tried
to help out in the freedom struggle so
everybody from this region
it is known
was trying their best to help out
the ina
of the great subachindra bose in its
quest to liberate india from the foreign
barbaric brutal occupier so everybody
from this region did what they could
they are all heroes but unfortunately
their names are not recorded there is a
museum the ina museum
in
in moirang
in manipur where is moirang
here it is
so there is an ina museum over here
somewhere here
where
you have photographs
of those old days
when the ina tried to liberate india
from the british so there were so many
great freedom fighters from the far east
of india but very few of them have been
recorded i would say that there would
still be records and memories of these
great people
i hope that the
esteemed historians
from the universities in manipur and
nagaland and assam and mizoram and
arunachal and meghalaya and tripura etc
i would hope that these historians from
these universities would do some actual
research
and publicize
these stories of struggle and and
freedom and the fight for freedom
so i hope these things happen in the
coming days weeks years months yeah
but that's what i can say in brief about
the freedom fighters from the far east
region of india
okay mr manoo narayan says what is
okay what is the source of your
information and claim
that there is indian dna in the
aboriginal aboriginal people of
australia
what is the source of your information
and claim that's what the question is so
uh
shall we
find out together shall we do it
let me share my screen
what we will do is we will go to google
the empty google page google
uh
search page and let's say
indian
dna in australian
abori genes aborigines right
so
let's click on the first link what does
it say
the story untold the links between
indian between australian aboriginal and
indian tribes and there is a whole story
here which tells you about
what happened
you have this
research paper from nature
nature
aboriginal australian genomes reveal
indian ancestry
read this
next let's go back out
let's see this one
genetic relationship between indian
tribes and australian aboriginals this
is another research paper from pubmed
let's go to the next one bbc
ancient migration genes link australia
with india
right this is a bbc article
let's go further abc.net.ou
research shows ancient indian migration
to australia once again you have all the
details here
let's go
further ahead sciencedirect.com gene
flow from the indian subcontinent to
australia evidence from the y chromosome
this is a research paper from current
biology shall i go on and on and on and
on
dear sir in the time it took you to type
this comment you could have found all
the all the information on your own
so i hope i have proven my claim
that there is indian dna in the
aborigines australian aboriginal people
look it up
do some research of your own
learn how to search for information
don't be dependent on one person
the
the reason i am answering all these
questions is not to
spoon feed you all information i am
hoping that
many of you
will
learn to search for information
yourselves it's very easy
to search for information every single
fact that i'm i'm putting out
i'm giving you references because i am
doing this extempore on the spot
but i am hoping that you people my dear
audience my dear viewers will take the
initiative to double check to cross
check what i'm saying and look it up for
yourselves
every single thing i am saying every
single fact i'm putting out
every single claim i'm making
it's evidence is available in the public
domain you just have to go and search
for it please please
learn how to search for information
don't ask me such questions
learn how to
seek out information if you have a
question if you can type it into the
youtube comments you can also type it
into google and look for the information
please do that
okay ayan says what do you think about
the telugu film industry is it the in
is the industry
working for improving india soft power
and representing india's film stream
culture through films like bahubali kgf
rr pushpa maggadira
kanchana etc etc
so out of all the films you have
mentioned i have seen
i have watched bahubali part 2 i liked
it i mean i i
i feel that some of these sequences
special effects and so on were a little
bit
over the top but that's fine
i loved the fact that it presented
indian culture in
in a respect in a respectful and good
light
if you look at bollywood if you watch
bollywood movies it constantly
repeatedly
demeans and denigrates indian culture
it makes fun of indian culture all the
time
if you watch a movie like bahubali you
get a whole different
view
a whole different
approach that they are using so they
actually respect indian culture they are
proud of their heritage and they are
they are taking the lead in showcasing
in india's culture ancient culture right
so i haven't seen other movies like
kgf rrr and all those things but from
baahubali i was i was very happy to see
bahubali
and if that trend is continuing it's a
very good thing so it does look like the
telugu film industry film industry is uh
is way more respectful of indian culture
and it portrays indian culture way more
accurately than something like bollywood
so that is a very good thing
and
if you do that it's going to improve
india's soft power
because it's going to showcase indian
culture the real indian culture genuine
indian culture in a positive way
worldwide because india's
entertainment history uh industry has a
global reach
so i think it's a very good thing and i
would like to commend the telugu film
industry for doing what bollywood
where is not willing to do so i'm really
happy to see this
charan says why was ching is khan called
khan a muslim surname what is the
history of surnames of muslims did they
exist before islamization of central
asia
look i am not an expert in the history
of surnames of the muslim people and all
i can tell you about changes khan
the term
khan
is not an arabic term it's not a muslim
term or an islamic term
the word khan
is the
mongol word for leader
khan means leader
in the mongol language and in also in
various turkic languages
before the today the turkic peoples are
almost all
most of them i would say especially in
turkey and other parts of central asia
most of them are muslims
there are target peoples who live in
siberia in the tungus region and all who
still follow tangerism or various
animistic practices but the majority of
turkey peoples overall are muslims today
but before the turks they became muslims
they were either
buddhists or hindus and before they
became buddhists or hindus they were
practitioners of the ancient
polytheistic culture called thangrism
it's an ism because the west calls
everything isms like hinduism buddhism
jainism and so on but
tangerism
is named after the sky god thangri
but it's a polytheistic belief system it
has the earth mother i think she's
called umai and there's a whole
pantheon of various other gods as well
in
the the
thing raised belief system
uh so that's what it is right so the
turks and the mongols
they were originally practitioners of
the english and the mongols still
practice tangirism in conjunction with
buddhism hinduism mostly it's called
buddhism
so
the word khan is
mongolic and turkic in origin the
ancestors of the mongolian turkic
peoples were the hunnic peoples so the
huns also called their leaders kings
chieftains as khans
so ching is khan was the great khan the
greatest khan of all time of the of the
mongol people
so that's why he was called khan because
he was the leader the king of the
mongols
he was the khan of khans it was a khagan
right
and then what happened is that the
mongols conquered the islamic world
chingashan's grandson hulegu khan
destroyed the
the penultimate caliphate
the baghdad caliphate i don't remember
which which one it was i think it was in
the year one two five eight if i am not
mistaken don't quote me on that
somewhere around there
that
and
the mongols
nearly obliterated the islamic world
nearly they came this close to that
but eventually they did not happen and
what happened is that the mongols
started ruling the islamic world
eventually they got intermixed with it
many of the mongol
rulers
or leaders of chieftains eventually
their descendants they intermingled they
intermarried with the turks and the
arabs and all that
they eventually themselves became
islamized and this title khan became a
prestige title in the islamic world
that's why so many muslims today have
the
surname or the title khan
because it came from the rulers of the
islamic world the mongols
so khan is not a muslim surname
it is a word that means
leader or ruler or king in the mongolian
language
it came into the islamic world
with the mongol conquest
of the islamic world so that i hope
explains why ching is
was known as khan even though he was not
a muslim in any way whatsoever
money says attempt number 982
what is the exact origin place of the
honnek people in the world map
and they are the descendants of which
people okay
let's
pinpoint it on the map
let me share the map
and let's take a look at where the
origin of the
people is
so this is a map of the
of eurasia
you know where india is let's go if you
are let's say in manipur nagaland
and you go straight north straight north
you will end up in mongolia
can you see that
right
due north of
the far east of india is mongolia
so this essentially this entire region
mongolia
the chinese occupied portion of mongolia
it's inner mongolia
and this entire region north of
present-day mongolia which is around
this lake lake baikal
all of this is the ancient homeland or
heartland you so you could say
of the ancient hunnic people the chinese
called these people the shionu
and they were known in the west as the
huns the huns they were known in ancient
india as the hunas
during the gupta during the later phase
of the gupta era the gupta empire era
there was wave after wave after wave of
of
invasions
in northern india and our great emperor
skanda gupta repelled them all
after his demise eventually the huns
were able to prevail
they invaded parts of india they took
over present day afghanistan gandhar
and various parts of northern india and
they assimilated into the indian
population they all became hindus some
of them remained atheists people like
mehirakula who was very evil
but most of them assimilated very
harmoniously into india and one of the
great
for instance
the great indian scientist brahma gupta
mathematician and astronomer his
patron
was a hornik origin king named
vyagramukha
from
bin mal in
in western india i'm not sure where it
is but you can look it up right so and
at the same time that the huns were the
shweta hunas were trying to invade india
at that very same time they were also
invading the roman empire so they were a
nomadic people who covered the entirety
of eurasia
but to come back to your question the
place of origin of the hanik people is
present-day mongolia and north of
mongolia this
overall
region right who were the ancestors of
the people well
we would need
deep genetic studies to find out
so that's
as far as i can go
about who the
people were and
where what was the place of origin that
we know about
all right
kok lang says
huge fan thank you so much sir i want to
ask you tripura is a small state from
the northeast of india during the
bangladesh liberation war a huge number
of bengali refugees came to tripura
never went back after
the situation became normal
now they have become a majority
and the native people have become a
minority in their very own land native
people are asking the government of
india for a solution but they don't pay
much heed to it
should the indian government not give
first preference to its own state people
first in terms of the cultural safety
and security
land and then think to bring policies
like ca because it can do exotics to
native people like living in assam and
tripura specifically and the culture and
identity after some hundred years if you
are to talk about humanity saving your
own indian is the first and foremost
kind of humanity
so
what you are saying sorry is absolutely
true
in 1971 there was this horrific genocide
that the pakistanis carried out in
bangladesh
in present present-day bangladesh
mostly hindus
between one to five million
people were massacred the americans
supported that and because of this there
was a huge exodus of hindus
into india
mainly
mainly into uh
what we now call northeast of india the
far east of india
many of them came into bengal and many
of them came into
tripura
now if you look at the history of
tripura it is the homeland of the
tripuri people who are
the original inhabitants of tripura
going back i don't know how many
centuries
but the tripuri people are the original
inhabitants the indigenous inhabitants
of tripura
after 1971 i don't know how many lakhs
of refugees
bengali hindu refuges came into tripura
they settled down
and today if you look at the population
of tripura it's majority bengal is
speaking nothing against the bengali
people but the government of india
should have
definitely
done something to safeguard
the uh the rights of the indigenous
people of tripura
today if you look at tripura you don't
even know that the tripuri people exist
there they have become a very small
minority they used to have a great
kingdom very in very
very beautiful and interesting culture
the tripuri culture the tripuri kingdom
tippura kingdom today you see no trace
of that and there are very few tripuri
people that you know of there was this
this lady
what's her name uh she was a winner of
one of the indian idol
seasons her name was saurabh dave verman
i think
i have no idea what happened to her but
yeah that is one example of a person
that belongs to the
original indigenous people of tripura
so i agree that what happened in tripura
is terrible
the entire state was taken over by by
refugees and today they are essentially
permanent inhabitants of that
so yeah it's tragic and i don't know
what's the solution now it's been so
long like 40 how many years has it been
40 years 50 years
something like that it's been several
decades it's almost impossible to undo
these demographic changes after so long
the government should have taken care of
this issue at that time
now what do you do i really don't know
so this is the kind of situation you
have in india
and it's something that's still going on
in a variety of ways
and it's something this country needs to
deal with
in the long run if we don't want a
disastrous demographic change
because of
you know demographic engineering which
is what happened in tripura
so i agree that what happened it needs
to be recognized something needs to be
done to preserve the cultural
integrity of whatever remains
of the original culture of tripura
something needs to be done about that i
think the government of tripura should
take care of it or the central
government should take care of it but
something certainly needs to be done
aj rana says can you shed some light on
the history of gunpowder in india as
i've heard that it was first invented in
china
is it true or a partial truth so uh
i expect that if you go to wikipedia
wikipedia will tell you that gunpowder
was invented in china i think wikipedia
says that gunpowder was invented in
china somewhere somewhere around the 8th
or 9th century about
11 or 1200 years before today that's
what they claim that's what wikipedia
says now as i have said many times in
the past wikipedia is not a reliable
source of information especially when it
pertains to indian history and indian
culture
so what is the truth
so let me uh
share
my screen
and share a certain
text
with you
let's do it now let's do it right away
so this is
by dr gustav oppert who was a german
indologist who says that gunpowder
originated in ancient india let's read
the first
the the beginning paragraph
the invention of gunpowder has been
ascribed to different individuals
belonging to different countries and as
the question as to its authorship and
antiquity is still an open one
we shall discuss the moot point and
shall endeavor to prove that the oldest
documents mentioning and describing
gunpowder
are found in india
and written in sanskrit and that the use
of gunpowder and its application to the
discharge of missiles
from projectile weapons was a well-known
fact in ancient india corroborating so
far the opinion of those who have always
pointed out india as the original seat
of its invention
the question whether china received the
knowledge of gunpowder or from india or
vice versa cannot be touched here and so
on no chinese work on this question can
with respect to antiquity be compared
with this
so even if the chinese should have
independently invented gunpowder the
claim as to priority of invention will
certainly remain with india
so the
oldest known
reference
to gunpowder to agni churna
is in the ancient indian text called the
shukraniti
shukraniti which is ascribed to the
ancient sage shukracharya
what's interesting is that the
shukraniti is referenced in the
mahabharata in the ramayana
and even the arthashastra
in the beginning pays obeisance
to shukracharya
so
we we know for a fact that the
arthashastra is about two and a half
thousand years old
and the arthashastra references
shukracharya who is the author of the
shukraniti the shukraniti has clear
references to gunpowder and to
projectile weapons that can fire
missiles that are based that have gun
powder as their
as their fuel
so it tells you how ancient the
knowledge of gunpowder was in india
so mini mum at the very least
two and a half or three thousand years
before today and most likely way way
older than that that's how old gunpowder
the knowledge of gunpowder was in india
most likely the chinese would have
acquired this knowledge
from india because there were ancient
contexts very extensive ancient contexts
between india and china and india was a
net exporter of culture a massive net
exporter of culture ideas knowledge
wisdom to china
china absorbed all of that from india so
most likely the chinese got this
knowledge from india
so it is very clear despite what
wikipedia says despite what all your
eminent historians will say it is very
clear that gunpowder was first invented
in india the knowledge of gunpowder in
india goes back at least at the very
least two and a half thousand years
before today
okay regulus says hi i am from latin
america most
specifically mexico i wanted to ask you
what are your views on strengthening
ties between india and latin america
since the chinese are already settling
they're setting their influence in
places like argentina i think they would
quickly start colonizing us with their
companies and there isn't much we can do
since innovation is unfortunately not
something associated with hispanic
countries including spain
so in my opinion it would become
necessary to increase our ties with
india the problem is that india is
usually overlooked when it comes to
foreign relationships
in basically most latin american nations
and i also don't really know if this
would
convene india so i want to know your
views about this subject
a very interesting question and what's
even more interesting is that the
foreign minister of argentina
is right now as we speak in india and
it's also very interesting that today
he held a
a presentation a meeting a conference
what it was
about the status of the malvinas islands
the malvinas islands are known in the
english-speaking world as the falkland
islands they are currently occupied by
the united kingdom even though they are
right next to argentina and argentina
has a claim on these islands a historic
claim on islands but the british have
currently
captured and occupied this islands
so the
foreign minister
of argentina
on indian soil
gave a presentation
[Music]
about the status of the malvinas islands
exactly in the same room
and from the same spot where 48 hours
before
the uk prime minister boris johnson had
made an address isn't that very
interesting
so it is an indicator
of a certain
strengthening
of the relationship between india and
argentina
coming closer of the two nations in a
certain way
i believe that the
chief guest in the
recent republic day celebrations in
india was
whether it is this one or the previous
republic day it was the president of
brazil mr bolsonaro so there again you
see some kind of cooperation happening
some kind of relationship building
happening
i'm not sure what the relationship
between india and mexico is but it is
now very clear that india is making a
significant diplomatic
outreach
to latin america
we may still it may still take some time
for its
results to be visible on the ground
but there is
an increasing focus
in india towards latin america
especially the larger countries like
brazil and argentina i would also
consider mexico to be a very important
country in latin america and i'm sure
that india
will be focusing on mexico as well i
think there is a great deal of
um
affinity
in a variety of ways between india and
mexico right so
and as you say the chinese have been
making moves in latin america for at
least the past
12 to 15 years
and we know very well what sort of
checkbook diplomacy
they employ
they
go and target the corrupt politicians in
various countries and they have a
significant
significant amount of funding that they
can offer to these corrupt politicians
which gives them access to all the
resources of these countries they have
been doing this in africa in sri lanka
they've tried that with nepal they've
tried it with various south east asian
countries
they have tried it in various latin
american countries and it will
eventually
if this continues result in the chinese
colonization of these countries and the
chinese will become masters of all the
resources
the raw materials natural resources that
these countries can provide
so that would not be beneficial for the
people of the country and the economy of
the country that will not be a good
thing
on the other hand india does not engage
in such
predatory practices india tries to
engage in mutually beneficial
relationships
so i would say that india would be a
much better partner
for the countries of latin america and
all relationships should be
based on mutual benefit and mutual
respect
so i think india can offer
a much better deal of course india does
not have the deep pockets to give bribes
the chinese can and that's why maybe
some some in some countries the
politicians or the leaders may not be so
open to welcoming india at this stage
i have said in the past all countries
do not unfortunately pursue their
national interest
sometimes you have certain politicians
who pursue their own personal interests
and which is why countries suffer
especially when they have these corrupt
politicians while ruling them i am not
specifying any any country in particular
but
it has been known
that
in southern america in latin america
there has been corruption
and there have been corrupt leaders in
the past so that's one factor that we
have to be uh cognizant of right
so i would certainly say that india is
going to focus more
more on latin america in the coming
years the coming decade for sure
and i hope to see closer cooperation and
more indian investment
into the in these countries and better
relationships economic relationships
diplomatic relationships even
people-to-people relationships tourism
trade and all those things
which will be really good for india as
well as latin america
so that's something that i am
really hopeful about
suraj says what would be the consequence
if india had not developed nuclear
weapons
had india not developed nuclear weapons
india would be at china's mercy today if
india was not were not to be already
broken by china
the only nation in asia that can stand
up to china and
challenge china in a variety of ways
whether it's economically or culturally
or militarily
is india that's the only nation that the
chinese are worried about that's the
only nation the chinese are afraid of
and today the chinese economy is five
times almost five times that of india
five times there of india
and they have a much more massive
military budget
they are modernizing their military
their navy and all so they have a
significant advantage over india the
only thing that is holding the chinese
back
is the indian nuclear deterrent
right
so had india not developed nuclear
weapons
the whole story would be different the
chinese would have already taken over
parts of india quite possibly the
pakistanis would have been much more
emboldened
and even the relationship with other
countries would have been very different
when you are a nuclear power you have a
certain stature a certain status on the
geopolitical chess board you are one of
a small group of elite nations
and you have a certain amount of hard
power that nobody can deny and nobody
can trifle with
even the relationship between india and
america would have been very different
had india not developed nuclear weapons
and the ability to deliver them at large
at long distances
so we don't quite know what india's
delivery
mechanisms
are
we have a variety of nuclear missiles
with different ranges
we have certain nuclear missiles that
can be classified as intercontinental
ballistic missiles
icbms like the agni 5
there may be certain other missiles in
our arsenal
that may have even longer ranges than
the agni 5.
these are
matters that are not discussed in public
these are classified matters
but
it gives you a certain leverage
when even when dealing with a very very
powerful nation
so had india not developed nuclear
weapons india would not be in the
position that it is today india is today
becoming
a major pole
a major global pole in the geopolitical
multi-polar geopolitical world order
had india not developed nukes india
would not be that india would not be in
that position
so uh india first tested nuclear a
nuclear device in 1974 i believe and
then promptly
closed the program shelved it and left
it to rot
it is only in 1998 that the second bunch
of tests was done and that's when india
officially declared that it is now a
proper nuclear power whether you like it
or not
and then the americans impose sanctions
on india all the
western european vassal states condemned
india and imposed a variety of
of uh
measures on india but india overcame
that
over time
and in the long run
it really bolstered india's position
globally from the perspective of hard
power
so that is
the consequence of having nuclear
weapons it gives you
a significant deterrent against bullies
and rogue nations like china it also
elevates your stature globally on the
geopolitical chess board
sharias says is the war between
afghanistan and
pakistan possible in the current
situation considering recent airstrikes
of pakistan on afghan land
while afghanistan and pakistan have
unfinished business
the afghans claim a sizable portion of
territory that is currently
in the hands of pakistan
so the north-west frontier province is a
place of pakistan
which is currently in pakistan
has the pashtun majority population
and
they wish to be part of afghanistan they
are pashtuns they they consider the
territory to be pashtunistan the
pakistani government isn't quite in 100
in control of this of this region
there is a reasonably open and porous
border with afghanistan so there is a
long-standing
territorial dispute between afghanistan
and pakistan the afghans claim pakistan
and territory and the pakistanis don't
want to give it
right
so that is a conflict that's been there
for a very long time since
well essentially since the
1820s and 1830s
since the days of the great maharaja
ranjit singh
so uh that's a whole
different backstory that i will not go
into right now so afghanistan claims
territory currently occupied by pakistan
which is pashtun majority
now in recent times there have been
multiple clashes between pakistan and
afghanistan afghanistan is now ruled by
the taliban the americans handed over
pakistan to the handed over power
in afghanistan to the taliban terrorists
who are now the
rulers of afghanistan
and there have been clashes in recent
times
just a week or two ago the pakistani air
force conducted airstrikes in
official afghan territory killing a
large number of
innocent civilians men women children
that's what the pakistanis did because
they can
so the question is is a war between
these two nations possible
see
afghanistan which is essentially the
taliban is in no position
[Music]
to fight a conventional war with
pakistan the pakistani army
is a professional army it's a
well-trained army it can certainly
overwhelm afghanistan any time it likes
it is not quite as professional and as
well trained as the indian army it is no
match for the indian army
but it it can certainly take care of
afghanistan a bunch of taliban fighters
are
they they are nothing compared to the
pakistani army especially the kind of
uh
equipment the pakistanis have they have
tanks they have a proper air force with
f-16s and various chinese fighter planes
and so on so they can so the taliban
doesn't stand a chance in a conventional
war with pakistan
and the pakistanis of course have nukes
which are for india not for afghanistan
now
what the taliban can do
is to wage
a
non-conventional
war with the pakistanis which means
their typical
tactics of
insurgency
right freedom fighting insurgency
whatever you want to call it
when it comes to pakistan we'll call it
that
so that's what the taliban can do
they have a significant amount of
support in the north west for frontier
province lots of prestons live there
lots of pashtuns live in karachi in
other parts of pakistan
so there is always a potential of the
taliban using that of the afghans using
that advantage against pakistan
so i don't see a full-fledged war
erupting between pakistan and
afghanistan
but i don't see the relationship being a
normal relationship being a stable
relationship being a cordial or friendly
relationship
people viewed the pakistanis as
essentially owning afghanistan which is
not quite the case
the taliban
are afghan nationalists and they do not
like being under the boots of the isi
the pakistani isi
so it's a complex situation but
i expect
the thing the the relationship
to deteriorate further in the
coming
months and years
it's not going to be a fun time for
pakistan
but i don't see a
full-fledged war also happening it may
be a
low-intensity conflict
for the time being
kevin says
what's the historical significance of
the city baruch in gujarat
i had recently come to know through
wikipedia that my city baruch is the
second oldest indian city
having continuous habitation let's take
a look at the city of baruch where
exactly is it
let me go to the map and let's see where
baruch is
so baruch like kevin says is in
western india in the state of gujarat
so it is somewhere north
there it is the city of baruch
which is a city on the narmada river the
great river narmada one of the great
rivers of
india
now baruch was uh historically
a port city as you can see it's quite
close close to the sea there's a nice
natural harbor here
and it's a very old city
so the original name of the city of
baruch was
it's a sanskrit name
and
it is believed that the great rishi
bhrigu
he came to this place sitting on a
turtle on a tortoise
so the city uh so the word for tortoise
in sanskrit is kach
which is where the hindi name kachwa
comes from then the word kachwa comes
from so
the combination of the words brigu and
the kach became
that is the name that is the original
sanskrit name of this city
it is uh supposed to be very old
and uh
so i don't know exactly what its
antiquity is i'm not sure if proper
archaeological work has been done here
to establish the oldest date of
inhabitation
but it was certainly part of the
territory of the ancient saraswati hindu
civilization phase of our civilization
the whole of gujarat saurashtra kach and
much of the north west northern and
western region of india was part of this
extensive
uh urbanized phase of our civilization
including
or baruch
so it may it must be really really old
now uh
it was
the capital of the indus kitchen king
nahapana
lived about 2000 years before today he
is mentioned in the ancient greek text
the periplus of the erythrian sea
so they have a greek name barzigara or
something like that for the city baruch
and
they named this king nambanus or naha
panna who was a indus keithian king a
very good king very powerful king who
did lots of cultural works like
like for ins for instance there is this
cave there are these caves in the city
of mumbai the canary caves krsnagiri
caves they were constructed
on the orders of
and
various other things so the his capital
was the city of baruch
and various other subsequent india indus
kitian kings mahak chakrapuras like
rudra simha and rudra dharman also
ruled from this region
and even during the rajput era the
solanki era etc barrows was a major city
and then of course you had the
the turkic invasion of gujarat and then
i think the city went into kind of
decline today baruch i think is not a
very big city as you can see it's not
it's not a very large city it's a
medium to small sized town
but it has a great glorious past and
hopefully a great future as well so
that's what i can say
in brief
about the city of
baruch
okay dungar singh johann says please
please
please answer this time why isn't there
a clear acceptance that rebirth exists
recently there was a four-year-old girl
in
raj samantha rajasthan who clearly spoke
facts about her past life
india is full of such unambiguous cases
of rebirth then what else does science
need
to accept the fact that rebirth exists
when there are so many evidences in
front of us so let's understand
what is
evidence
in court
if somebody says i saw this
then that is admissible evidence as a
witness
so that is legally admissible evidence
that doesn't mean it's scientific
evidence scientific evidence has to be
unambiguous and incontrovertible
so what is so let's understand what
rebirth is rebirth is tied to the
concept of karma
in the abrahamic worldview you have one
life
when you die your soul goes into some
place
and then there is some guy who will
either allow you to go to heaven or dump
you into hell so that is the abrahamic
concept in in a very
brief nutshell
in the dharmic worldview
the soul the atma
is
immortal
and um when a person dies they
accumulate
all the
uh
fruits of their actions good actions bad
actions that which is called karma
and karma is something it's a conserved
quantity it is it's like there's a law
of conservation of karma
the
fruits of your actions they are
conserved bit over lifetime so your soul
is immortal
after you die
your soul goes to eventually another
body you are reborn
and the karma which you had accumulated
in your past lifetime it continues into
the new lifetime so that is the concept
of karma and there is a concept of
rebirth
so
to clearly establish
the linkage
between person a who died in person b
who was born and claims to be
a reincarnation of person a
one would need to establish one to one
correspondence of the soul
the the soul that was in person a
who died is the soul that the same soul
that is now migrated to person b
that would be the
unambiguous proof
of the existence of rebirth
now can we observe the soul
can we measure the soul
unfortunately we cannot
and therefore it is not scientific
evidence that is how science works
a million people can make claims that i
have seen a ghost or i have been reborn
or i have had a conversation with god
those are non-provable scientifically
because you cannot replicate that
phenomenon in a measurable way you
cannot photograph it
you cannot videograph it
you cannot measure it
that is simply how science work you
cannot mix
religion
spirituality and science these are
different domains or philosophy and
science
science has certain criteria which
cannot be mixed up with
the criteria that philosophy has or
spirituality has or religion has right
so
because of that i mean i i agree i agree
with what dungeon is saying there are so
many cases that seem extraordinarily
convincing i mean how can a four year
old kid remember
things a four-year-old kid who has never
been to a certain place say exactly what
is there about the life of a certain
person it's it's incredible
so it is incredible
it's it's a like
it's very convincing isn't it and yet
you cannot prove it scientifically
so it's so when it comes to spirituality
when it comes to religion
or when it comes to philosophy it's
about belief
you don't need proof if you believe it
if you have the belief you why do you
need proof
so
we cannot bring this into the realm of
science
we have to also understand that there
are things that science has limitations
science is unfortunately very imperfect
it's because of the limitations of our
intellect we humans are actually
very unintelligent
our intelligence has very very very
hard limits so there are so many things
that we don't understand so many things
that science doesn't explain cannot
explain as of today there are so many
things that science is unable to explain
today
95 percent of the universe
is
dark
science has no idea what it is we are
able to understand only a fraction of
five or four percent of the universe
that too very very imperfectly so there
is a whole lot that science cannot
explain maybe in the future when humans
become more intelligent we may be able
to bring certain other things into the
realm of realm of science
but as of today
rebirth karma all of these things
cannot be proven or disproven
scientifically and therefore they cannot
come into the realm of science but that
doesn't prevent anybody from believing
them some cases are are incredibly
convincing aren't they i agree
but yet you cannot say but so let's not
try to prove it with science if you
believe it believe it that's all that
matters what
to you
what you believe matters whether it is
scientific or unscientific is not
important what matters is what you
believe so it's up to you it's up to
every individual to decide to choose
what you believe or don't not believe
and that's all that matters eventually
alpha says shouldn't basic education and
health care be free for the citizens
in my opinion
in any civilized society
education
health care and justice should be
completely free for everybody for all
citizens
education
health care
and justice
these three things should be completely
free and completely accessible to all
citizens no matter what their age is no
matter what their gender is no matter
what their social class or wealth is
doesn't matter
everybody should get the same education
should have the same access
to the same education the same high
quality health care and
speedy justice that is the hallmark of a
civilized society
do you know in after 1947 in certain
princely states of india
you still had free education and free
health care
if you felt sick if you had some if you
had some medical issue you would be
given free treatment high quality
treatment
in a hospital
that was paid for by the local king or
whatever
then when the princely states were
abolished the government of india took
away all these rights and privileges
from the citizens and today you have the
commercialization of health care
which i in my opinion is barbaric
you should not have to pay for health
care in a civilized society
your access to health care should not
depend on how much money you have
everybody should have access to good
health care
everybody pays taxes
yeah i know that only a small percentage
of indians pays income tax but everybody
pays gst
any
good that you buy any goods you buy a
kilo of tomatoes there is gst on that
that is going into the coffers of the
government
you buy any service there is gst on that
you go to a restaurant there is gst on
that anything that you purchase
there is gst applied on that so every
citizen of india is paying taxes
so today india is unfortunately still a
broken country india is a country that
is struggling to rise it will rise in
the next 10 20 years
india will i will consider india to be a
civilized country a proper civilization
again
only when it is able to provide high
quality free education free health care
and speedy justice to all of its
citizens
irrespective of
anything
so yes i agree
mignot says it has been
known that an indian the great
bodhidharma introduced martial arts into
china and various other countries in
eastern asia
and these countries were able to
preserve these martial arts and their
culture till date
why did we indians fail to preserve
these things
good question
let me offer a different perspective
today is
the 24th of april
a day or two ago
somewhere i think in rajasthan
a couple of ancient temples were
demolished by the government
these these temples were like two or
three hundred years old heritage temples
ancient temples they were destroyed by
the
government state government of that
place
even today you indians my dear friends
us we indians
even today
we are unable to preserve our heritage
that is your answer
we have
for the past 1 000 years
been ruled by people
who have wanted
to destroy our heritage to destroy our
culture
the millennium of humiliation
and such people still exist today such
governments
still exist today they are still
actively working to destroy our culture
our heritage and our civilization
that is your answer that is why we were
unable to preserve our martial arts we
are still unable
to save our temples whatever is left of
them and we are still not allowed to
administer our temples
good answer
okay
abhishek says
how to become friends with girls
i'm 20 years old i have never had a
female friend in my whole life
okay abhishek
okay forget about a girl or a boy how do
you make friends
it's very simple
you will not make friends unless you go
and talk to people
unless you go and speak with people
so that's the first thing if you want to
have
female friends
you have to first go and speak to
females
and then if if two people have some
things in common some interest in common
or some something in common then a
friendship may
may be possible
so you will not have a female friend if
you never go and speak to females so
that's the first thing go and speak to
to everybody males females everyone
right
so that's the first thing and secondly
be who you are be open be
be yourself
don't try to pretend don't pretend to be
something you are not don't try to
impress anyone if you
if you are worried about impressing
people
you're gonna look fake
and you will not look authentic just be
who you are and don't care about what
people think
go and talk to people and hopefully you
will have friends so that's what i can
say in very brief
all the best sir
okay let's take one more question for
today
anime says what are your tips on staying
away from
or not getting bothered by
petty fights like road rage street
brawls aggressive arguments social media
quarrels etc
how are you able to exhibit a calm and
composed presence every time even when
you get blasted with some mean and
disrespectful comments
me calm and compose
you see
the me
you see here
is just one small
aspect of who i am
i'm not always
calm and composed
actually i am known to have
somewhat of a temper
so
see when you see a person
on the media
they are in a controlled environment
and they want to put the best foot
forward
so what you see is not the entirety of
the person it is just one the public
aspect of the person
so i'm not always calm and composed
i see i mean i see all kinds of comments
every single day sometimes i want to
yeah
you know
so
so i'm not always calm and composed but
overall you should
try and cultivate
a
peaceful attitude try and meditate or
something
so my tips for staying away from petty
fights and and quarrels and all that
and being calm and composed all the time
firstly it's not possible to always be
calm and composed sometimes it's okay to
not be calm and composed the second
thing is
have a bigger objective
have a big goal that you're working
towards
something like a five year goal or a ten
ten year goal and you are working every
day towards that every day you're making
some progress towards that if you have a
big objective
something that is really really
important to you
and something that will take a lot of
work
over a period of years then these small
things will not
bother you you will find these things
unimportant you will try to stay away
from that because you have a much bigger
project
to work on
so the people who are
who are very easy to to rile
the people who are easy to distract
other people who have no big
big
big objective in their life
people who are aimless
they will get into fights all the time
people who don't have a big objective a
big goal they will get into fights they
will have street brawls or arguments or
whatever it is somebody who has a great
mission
will be focused on the mission and they
will not have the time to get into
fights
so that's what i would say find whatever
it is that motivates you
find a big
mission for yourself
and pursue that
if you do that then
you will find yourself
staying calm staying focused and not
getting into pointless arguments and all
that
so that's what i can say in brief but
even if you have something it it's not
always possible to stay calm all the
time
all right
okay how about a few live comments live
questions do you have any live questions
let me take a few maybe two three i've
not done that for a while
okay let's see if there are any
questions
any questions from the live chat
do we have something
let me look let me look let me look
are tanks obsolete in modern warfare
with the development of anti-tank
systems as we can see in the ukraine
russia conflict
that's an interesting question i think
lots of things are slowly becoming
obsolete in modern warfare
tanks
they are very like
i spoke about warships right surface
warships slow moving large
warships very visible very enticing
targets very easy to kill with missiles
and torpedoes and all that
similarly
tanks also are kind of like that
tanks were first invented a hundred
years ago
tanks were used and i believe world war
one world war two and they have been
progressively improved upon you have all
kinds of new technologies and tanks like
reactive armor and
such things
but yeah they are becoming more and more
easy to kill tanks
so i think that tanks
may be going the way of the dodo
becoming more of more and more obsolete
especially when you have things like
loitering munitions and
kamikaze drones
anti-tank missiles that are very cheap
so yeah it's
possibly going in the direction it's
possibly becoming going to become
obsolete
sooner rather than later
okay let us see is there anything else
any other interesting questions
are the rajputs aryans
every bharatiya is an arya
all indians
are aryans
the term arya are the english or western
word aryan
originates from the sanskrit arya which
means noble or civilized and the
original civilization is india which
means all indians are aryans whether you
are tall or short you are male or female
whether you're black or white or green
or pink or whatever you are all aryans
whether you're rajput or maratha or sikh
or
asamis or manipuri or
telugu or tulu or sinhalese or tamil or
whatever you're all aryans you're all
arya that's all it is
okay let's take one more question
as you can see it's not always possible
to be very calm and composed
all right
um
is there anything else
what is your favorite food
i'm dying to know
this my favorite food
i like all kinds of food
right now i don't mind eating a nice
vegetable salad
with some fried paneer how about that
what kind of entertainment do you have i
mean genres
i'm a big fan of watching movies
watching series nowadays around for the
time i enjoy watching podcasts but i
haven't seen a full fledged podcast in
like a year now
but yeah i am a big fan of entertainment
i'm a big fan of watching movies
especially in the big cinema halls
if i would have the time i don't mind
watching two or three movies in a cinema
hall every week
so yeah i like that i like music as well
do you watch anime these days i haven't
i don't watch anime at all but
when i was a kid i used to love watching
anime
right
um
your thoughts on cricket getting into
olympics 2028 and do you think kabady
would ever be an olympic sport
i think cricket is too
extended of a game to to make it to the
olympics i mean even the short version
of cricket takes about three hours right
a 2020 match
so
maybe it's not the best fit for the
olympic games cupboard i hope it becomes
an olympics for sport i'm a big fan of
kabaddi
it's a very physical sport it's a
contact sport
it's a it's a game of skills i mean
there are all kinds of skills involved
in kabaddi there are i mean
thin light players have a role to play
in kabaddi big bulky massive guys like
me have a role to play in kabaddi so
it's it's a it's a great game
i hope cupboard day becomes an olympic
sport it's a it's a game that can catch
on in the entire world if it is marketed
right
okay
is there anything else that i should
take up
deepam goswami what tell us something
about bengali brahmanas eating mutton
chicken
let them eat i say i mean it's a
personal choice
what are bengalis racially bengalis my
dear friends are indians
racially okay
let me see
will india be the next super power
india is currently
getting into pole position as one of the
major poles in a multipolar world
so next superpower
i am not quite sure
which will be the next superpower
currently the us is the only superpower
china wants to displace the us and
become the superpower
i hope that doesn't happen because china
doesn't have good intentions the chinese
communist party is not a force of good
in the world
so i hope
that india rises to the occasion and
becomes the next superpower i hope so
but
it is foolhardy to make
predictions
especially of something that will happen
that may happen in the next 20 30 years
20 30 years down the line
why are electric scooters catching fire
well i have not heard of such news but
electric scooters and all electric
vehicles
they run on these battery packs
and the battery packs have a certain
have a certain chemistry
they are essentially made of lithium
lithium-ion cells they are
and so
there has been there have been reports
of various electric cars occasionally
catching fire of various cell phones
cell phone battery packs catching fire
sometimes and the same technology exists
in electric scooters so maybe that's the
reason why it may be happening so that's
what i can offer you about this
was maharana pratap really 7.4 feet tall
or it's just a myth well there is no way
of corroborating him because see
there's no evidence
of how tall he was there are accounts
that he was a very tall strong man sure
that sort of thing he was clearly a very
great warrior
a
very brave man a very great ruler
so when somebody is that brave as a
person and that great as a ruler
typically you tie you tend to see them
as a very tall person so maybe that's
the reason
that the truth is it doesn't matter how
tall he was
what matters is how great he was he
stood alone against the might of the
turks
and he did not allow them to win
he fought his entire life
that he that is his great achievement
okay
where is the virus now it's lost
somewhere between russia ukraine it's
not that important anymore because there
are bigger fish to fry for the for the
west
when the time is right they will bring
it out of the closet i expect
okay what else
is
[Music]
real there is no evidence of it being
real
we now have a very good idea of what the
sea floor looks like and there is no
lost continent anywhere
so unfortunately it looks like this is
either a myth or
or we still don't have an explanation
but from the evidence that we have which
is very clear and unambiguous evidence
there is no lost continent to the south
of india so
from that evidence it doesn't seem to be
real
okay okay okay do we have anything else
okay i guess we're done for today
so everybody thank you so much for all
your questions great fun as always and i
will see you
in the next episode which is going to be
the first triple digit episode of ask
kabukit until then
take care thank you to everybody who
watches thank you to everybody who
supports this channel in whichever way
in a variety of ways thank you to all of
you
take care i will see you in the next
episode